Guide to the New York University Department of History Oral History Class Collection OH.033
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series II. 1995 Oral History Class Interviews, 1.4 Linear Feet in 2 half manuscript boxes, 1 media box, and 2 card catalog drawers.; 2 videocassettes (vhs); 1 videocassettes (hi8); 3 videodiscs (dvd); 35 audiocassettes; 47 sound discs (cd)
  - East Harlem Protestant Parish Interviews, 1995
    - Rios, Candida and Rosa Leon, 1995 November 11 (Box 16, Cassette 147, Box 7, Cd 10)
      Candida Rios was born in 1924 in Puerto Rico and was one of ten children. She married and had three children. In 1949 the family migrated to the United States (US) from Puerto Rico and settled in the East Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. She managed the household and was an active member of the Church of the Living Hope in East Harlem. Her husband served as the district leader of East Harlem in the 1950s and 1960s and served as a lay minister for the East Harlem Protestant Parish.
      Rosa Leon was born in 1945 in Puerto Rico and was the oldest daughter of Carlos and Candida Rios. She migrated to the US with her family in 1949.
      These interviews were conducted on November 11, 1995 by Liz Renner in the Bronx, New York. The majority of the interview with Candida Rios covers her memories of her husband's political career. She recalls migrating to the United States (US) with her husband, Carlos Rios, in order for him to become politically engaged in the Democratic Party in the US. She describes her husband's passion for civil rights and the fact that he was admired by the residents of East Harlem. She recalls finding community at the Church of the Living Hope in East Harlem, due to the majority of the congregation being bilingual. Rosa Leon's interview covers her memories of her father, Carlos Rios, and the active role he played in the religious and political aspects of the East Harlem community. Leon describes the fact that her father started an annual food drive for low income East Harlem families during the Thanksgiving season. She recalls her parents hosting community gatherings in their apartment. Leon explains her philosophy regarding religious beliefs and church attendance.
      Duration: 1:34:05
  - Immigration and Assimilation Interviews, 1995
    - Biederman, Billie, 1995 November 8; cuid240 (Box 8, Video 3, Box 1, Folder 123, Box Shared Tamiment 123, Dvd 27)
      Billie Biederman was born in 1924 at Beth Israel Hospital in Manhattan, New York. Her family was Jewish and she had two siblings. Her parents immigrated to the United States from Russia, her father in 1911 and her mother in 1920. Her family lived on Ludlow Street in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan. Her father was a musician in the Yiddish theatre and band leader, and her mother worked as a janitor in one of the buildings in which the family lived. Biederman graduated from Seward Park High School in the LES in 1940. She worked as a theatrical manager and as an executive assistant. Between 1948 and 1951 she lived in California and worked as a writer.
      This interview was conducted on November 8, 1995 by Christian Turek at an unspecified location. This interview was videotaped. The interview covers Billie Biederman's life in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Biederman discusses her working life and education. She discusses her regret at not having a religious Jewish education as a child. She describes her parents, their immigration experiences, and their working lives. She describes her mother's responsibilities as a janitor of the building in which the family lived on Ludlow Street in the LES and describes the family's apartment on Ludlow Street. She states that she visited the apartment around the time of the interview and relates her astonishment at the fact that her family and their boarders fit into the apartment. She discusses traditions in her family around Jewish holidays and food her mother would prepare for the family. She describes games she would play with her friends and other social and leisure activities in which she participated in the LES. She discusses anti-Semitism in the United States and her experiences of confronting anti-Semitic people in social situations. She discusses her working life after high school, including living in California between 1948 and 1951 and working as a writer. Other topics include customs in the LES around holidays, food in the LES, and Biederman's memoirs.
      Duration: 1:32:59
    - Birns, Leon, Undated
      The interviewer, date, and location of this interview are unknown. The audio recording for this interview is missing.
    - Ortiz-Arroyo, Roberto, 1995 December 11; cuid239 (Box 8, Video 2, Box 1, Folder 124, Box Shared Tamiment 123, Dvd 26)
      Roberto Ortiz-Arroyo was born in the 1940s in New York, New York. His parents migrated to the United States from Puerto Rico and were not married to each other. His father worked as a clerk for the United States Postal Service. His mother worked as a factory worker. Ortiz-Arroyo had three step-siblings, two of whom lived with Ortiz-Arroyo and their mother in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan. He was raised Catholic and converted to the Episcopal Church. He attended a Ukrainian Catholic school and an unspecified public middle school in Manhattan. He graduated from Seward Park High School in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan before taking classes at City College in Manhattan. He worked as a reporter and news announcer.
      This interview was conducted on December 11, 1995 by Christian Turek at an unspecified location. This interview was videotaped. The interview covers Roberto Ortiz-Arroyo's family and his life in Manhattan, New York. Ortiz-Arroyo discusses his parents and their lives in Puerto Rico and in the United States, including his mother's experiences in New York as a single parent in the 1940s and her illness and death from Alzheimer's disease. He describes his childhood in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan and his extended family in the LES. He discusses his education and describes his experiences at a Ukrainian Catholic school and the isolation he felt as the only Latino student in the school. He recounts his insecurities around speaking English, particularly problems understanding English idioms as a child and the way in which he became comfortable speaking English as an adult He discusses his conversion to the Episcopal Church from Catholic Church and reactions friends and family had to his conversion. Throughout the interview he describes his experiences as the only Latino person in groups and organizations to which he belonged and his feelings about these experiences.
      Duration: 1:04:13
    - Walker, Ray Weinstein, 1995 November 6 (Box 16, Cassette 139A-139B, Box 1, Folder 125, Box 6, Cd 39, Box 7, Cd 1)
      Ray Weinstein Walker was born in New York, New York in 1935 to a Jewish family. Her father was born in Russia and lived in England before immigrating to the United States. Her mother emigrated from Poland. Walker had one brother and one sister. She received a Bachelor of Arts degree, likely from the University at Albany, State University of New York, and a Master's degree in Communication from Denver University in Colorado. She worked as an office manager in a machine shop and as a high school English teacher. She taught English in Israel and traveled in Morocco.
      This interview was conducted on November 6, 1995 by Christian Turek at an unspecified location. Portions of the interview are unintelligible because of a recording error. Ray Weinstein Walker discusses her family, her education, and her career. She discusses her parents obtaining money to immigrate to the United States (US). She describes the ethnic diversity and tenements of the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Walker describes locating extended family members who immigrated to various countries as a result of World War II. Walker discusses learning to dance as a child and performing professionally at a farm in the Catskill Mountains in New York. Walker discusses teaching in English in Israel and becoming a Vietnam War protestor upon her return to the US. She discusses traveling to Morocco, Canada, and England. Walker describes maintaining Jewish traditions. She discusses creative projects such as writing a utopian play, taking a television production course at Brooklyn College, New York, and working on scripts.
      Duration: 1:57:47
  - Immigration and Education Interview, 1995
    - Cisse, Tamser, 1995 November 6 (Box 1, Folder 126, Box 16, Cassette 131, Box 6, Cd 30)
      Tamser Cisse was born into a Muslim family in 1977 in Dakar, Senegal. He grew up speaking primarily French at both school and at home. When he was sixteen years old, he immigrated to the United States (US) to live with his father in New York, New York. Cisse struggled to learn English and attended English classes at an English Language Service (ELS) school in New York. He attended a private Catholic school in Brooklyn before transferring to Seward Park High School in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan.
      This interview was conducted on November 6, 1995 by Sandra Nguyen at Seward Park High School in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. The majority of the interview covers Tamser Cisse's experience as a student in Dakar, Senegal and adjusting to life in New York City. The interview is difficult to understand as the voices are frequently muffled. Cisse recalls his ideas of what the United States (US) would be like based upon American television programs he watched in Dakar including The Beverly Hillbillies, and his realization that the US was different from the way in which it was portrayed on television. At the time of the interview, Cisse was contemplating his future educational plans and discusses his options with the interviewer which include pursuing higher education at an American university.
      Duration: 51:68
    - Friday, Lenora, 1995 November 30 (Box 16, Cassette 133, Box 1, Folder 127, Box 6, Cd 32)
      Lenora Friday was born into a large family in a small village near Freetown, Sierra Leone. Before her immigration to the United States, she completed some high school. At the time of the interview, she attended Seward Park High School in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York.
      This interview was conducted on November 30, 1995 by Sandra Nguyen at Seward Park High School in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. The audio recording is difficult to understand as the voices are frequently muffled. The majority of the interview covers Friday's knowledge of West African languages and her memories of attending school in Sierra Leone. She states that she speaks Temne and Creole, in addition to English. She discusses differences between school in Sierra Leone and the United States, including the fact that teachers in Sierra Leone were more strict.
      Duration: 37:01
    - Jean, Clarence, 1995 November 17 (Box 2, Folder 1, Box 16, Cassette 132, Box 6, Cd 31)
      Jean Clarence was born in the United States (US) in the 1970s. Both of his parents immigrated to the US from Haiti. When he was one year old, his parents sent him to live with his grandparents in Haiti, where he lived for about sixteen years before returning to the US. At the time of the interview he lived with his aunt and cousin in New York, New York.
      This interview was conducted on November 17, 1995 by Sandra Nguyen at Seward Park High School in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. The majority of the interview covers Jean Clarence's experience growing up in Haiti. He discusses his childhood, including the fact that his parents sent him to live with his grandparents in Haiti when he was one year old, his experiences in school, and his recollections of American television programs in Haiti during the 1980s and 1990s. Clarence sometimes speaks in French and gives little detail in his responses.
      Duration: 42:12
    - Sarr, Abdourahmane "Abdul", 1995 November 13 (Box 2, Folder 2, Box 16, Cassette 130, Box 6, Cd 29)
      Abdourahmane "Abdul" Sarr was born in 1977 in Dakar, Senegal. Sarr grew up in a suburban neighborhood in Dakar and attended private Catholic elementary and high school through the eleventh grade. He grew up speaking French and Ouolof. In 1994 he immigrated to the United States in order to learn English and to attend an American university.
      This interview was conducted on November 13, 1995 by Sandra Nguyen at Seward Park High School in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. The majority of the interview covers Abdourahmane Sarr's experience as a student in Dakar, Senegal and his adjustment to life in New York City. He discusses the fact that he found learning English to be difficult, but found it to be a necessary skill he needed to learn in order to live in the United States (US). At the time of the interview, Sarr had been in the US for less than a year and was contemplating his future educational plans beyond Seward Park High School, including possibly attending an American university.
      Duration: 37:07
    - Tremont, Darline and Diedra L'Ouverture, Undated (Box 16, Cassette 134, Box 6, Cd 33)
      Darline Tremont was born in Port-au-Prince, Haiti. She lived with family friends in Haiti after her parents immigrated to the US. In an unspecified year, she immigrated to the US.
      Diedra L'Ouverture was born in a small town near Port-au-Prince, Haiti and was one of 28 children. At the time of the interview L'Ouverture was sixteen years old. When she was five years old, her family immigrated to Jamaica from Haiti due to her mother's involvement in an unspecified revolutionary group in Haiti. The family later immigrated to Cuba and to the United States (US). At the time of the interview, she lived with her mother and siblings on 143rd Street in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan, New York.
      This interview was conducted on an unspecified date by an unspecified interviewer at an unspecified location. The majority of the interview covers Darline Tremont and Diedra L'Ouverture's childhoods in Haiti. Tremont recalls growing up in a very structured household in which education held precedence. She explains her reasons for not practicing one particular religion and describes her belief in a greater force that is beyond the basic human existence. L'Ouverture recalls experiencing discrimination in each place she lived due to her family being practitioners of Vodou. She explains that the pantheon of Vodou brings her comfort and security. She discusses her experiences in the various countries and states in which she lived prior to New York City. Both Tremont and L'Ouverture discuss the common perceptions of Haitians and provide examples of discrimination they have faced, mostly regarding the common idea that Haitians are all poor and uneducated.
      Duration: 1:31:28
      Haitians -- New York (State) -- New York -- Interviews.; Vodou.
  - Public and Cooperative Housing in the Lower East Side Interviews, 1995
    - Davenport, Helen, 1995 December 1 (Box 15, Cassette 127A-127B, Box 2, Folder 3, Box 6, Cd 26-27)
      Helen Davenport was born in 1925 at Fordham Hospital in the Bronx, New York. In August 1909, her maternal great-grandparents, grandparents, and mother immigrated to the United States from Poland. Her parents divorced before her birth, and she was raised by her mother and stepfather in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan. Davenport attended Public School 110 (PS110) near Cannon and Delancey Street in the LES and Metropolitan Vocational School in Manhattan. In 1942, she married. Her husband was drafted into the United States Coast Guard during World War II and served until 1945. In 1954, the family to the Bernard M. Baruch Houses in the LES.
      This interview was conducted on December 1, 1995 by John P. Spencer at Helen Davenport's apartment within the Bernard M. Baruch Houses in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. The majority of the interview covers Davenport's childhood experiences growing up during the Great Depression in the LES. She recalls standing in bread and soup lines with her mother and great-grandparents. In the 1930s, Davenport's parents were not able to support the family financially and sent Davenport and her three siblings to a shelter at the Church of Saint Catherine of Genoa in Manhattan. Davenport and her siblings remained at the shelter for about a month until her father regained employment. She attended high school at the Metropolitan Vocational School in Manhattan. Davenport received leave from high school so that she could assist her mother with caring for her sister who had poliomyelitis. Davenport discusses the jobs she held as a teenager, including seamstress, babysitter, housecleaner, and as a mail clerk at American Steel in Brooklyn.
      Duration: 1:54:01
    - Karp, Richard, 1995 October 19 (Box 2, Folder 4, Box 16, Cassette 149A-149C, Box 7, Cd 13-15)
      Richard Karp was born in 1928 in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. His family was Jewish. His father was born in 1895 in the LES. Karp attended Public School 4 and Junior High School 188 in the LES. He graduated from Seward Park High School in the LES and received his bachelor's degree from Brooklyn College in Brooklyn. He worked as a teacher and a school administrator. He married and had four children.
      This interview was conducted on October 3 and October 19, 1995 by John P. Spencer at Richard Karp's apartment in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. The interview covers Karp's life in the LES, his family, and his experiences in the Amalgamated Dwellings in the LES. Karp discusses his parents and grandparents, their immigration experiences, and their lives in the LES. He describes the ethnic divisions in the LES in the early decades of the 20th century. He discusses his education and the schools he attended in the LES. He recounts customs in his family and in the LES around the Jewish holidays. He describes the apartments in which his family lived in the LES, the living arrangements, and the amenities and utilities in the apartments. He discusses the changes in the ethnic composition in the LES after World War II when many Jewish residents moved from New York City to Long Island, New York and his opinions on why this change occurred.
      Karp discusses his move to the Amalgamated Dwellings in the LES in 1953 and describes the apartments in which he and his family lived. He compares the Amalgamated Dwellings in Manhattan and in the Bronx and discusses the programs available in the Bronx. He describes his feelings about cooperative housing and his desire to maintain a friendly and hospitable community in the Amalgamated Dwellings in the LES. He discusses his family members who moved out of the LES, the reasons why they moved, and his reasons for staying. He discusses his working life and describes his work as a teacher and school administrator in public schools in New York City. He discusses his involvement in the Board of Directors and the House Committee of the Amalgamated Dwellings between 1955 and the time of the interview, and his reasons for joining the board. He describes Abraham Kazan and his role in development of the Amalgamated Dwellings, the relationship between Kazan and Robert Moses, and urban renewal in the LES in the 1950s and 1960s. He discusses the differences between the Amalgamated Dwellings in the LES and the Bronx in detail. He discusses the founding philosophy the Bronx and LES Dwellings, as well as other cooperative buildings in the LES. He describes the ethnic and religious identities of the residents of the LES and Bronx Dwellings and his opinion that the residents of the Bronx Dwellings were mainly working class, religious Jewish people and the residents of the LES Dwellings were middle-class, culturally Jewish people. He discusses the changes in the ethnic and racial composition of the LES in the 1950s and 1960s as a mainly Eastern European Jewish neighborhood to a Latino neighborhood, his opinions on the reasons for this change, and differences in the neighborhood before and after the change in its population. Other topics include his children and grandchildren and social and leisure activities in which he participated as a child and teenager in the LES.
      Duration: 3:56:14
      Apartment houses, Cooperative -- New York (State) -- New York.; Amalgamated Dwellings (New York, N.Y.)
    - Mildworm, Saul, 1995 October 18 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Saul Mildworm was born in 1914 in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. His family was Jewish and his parents immigrated to the United States from an unspecified European country. His father worked as a presser in a garment factory and his mother managed the household. Mildworm attended Seward Park High School in the LES and worked as a lawyer.
      This interview was conducted on October 18, 1995 by John P. Spencer at Saul Mildworm's office in Manhattan, New York. The audio recording for this interview was inaudible and was not included in the collection. The interview covers Mildworm's life in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan and his experiences with the cooperative housing movement in the LES in the 1950s.
    - Wertheim, Leonard, 1995 December 1 (Box 2, Folder 6, Box 16, Cassette 148A-148B, Box 7, Cd 11-12)
      Leonard Wertheim was born in 1942 in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. His family was Jewish. His father was born in 1903 in England as his family was immigrating to the United States from Austria-Hungary. He worked for the United States Postal Service for 40 years. His mother was born in the LES in 1904 and worked outside of the home in various jobs. Between 1942 and 1948 his family moved from Goerck Street to Baruch Place in the LES. Between 1948 and 1955, his family lived in the Lavanburg Homes in the LES and lived in the Bernard M. Baruch Houses in the LES between 1955 and 1957. From 1957 to the time of the interview, Wertheim lived in the Seward Park Cooperative buildings in the LES. He attended Public School 188. He graduated from Seward Park High School in the LES and received his bachelor's degree from City College in Manhattan. He worked for the New York City Board of Elections. He married his wife, Ellen Wertheim, in 1971. They had two children.